<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A methodicall preface prefixed before the epistle to the Romanes ...] Made by the right reuerend father in and faithfull seruant of Christ Iesus, Martin Luther ...</title>
            <title>Praefatio in Epistolam Pauli ad Romanos. English</title>
            <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06513</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16986</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105157</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840887</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840887</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5429</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06513)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5429)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 928:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A methodicall preface prefixed before the epistle to the Romanes ...] Made by the right reuerend father in and faithfull seruant of Christ Iesus, Martin Luther ...</title>
                  <title>Praefatio in Epistolam Pauli ad Romanos. English</title>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
                  <author>Wilkinson, William, d. 1613, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Watkinson, William, fl. 1573-1594, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from STC.</note>
                  <note>A translation, by William Watkinson or William Wilkinson of: Luther, Martin.  Praefatio in Epistolam Pauli ad Romanos.</note>
                  <note>Halkett &amp; Laing (3rd ed.) disputes attribution to Wilkinson.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A methodical preface of M. Luther before the epistle to the Romans.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A¹² (-A11-12) B-C¹²  D⁶.</note>
                  <note>Leaves marked, stained and cropped, with some loss of running title and signatures.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: title page as filmed too dark to read.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5429:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5429:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Methodicall preface prefixed befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Epiſtle of <hi>S. Paul</hi> to the <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erie neceſſarie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able for the be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> vnderſtanding of it.</p>
            <p>Made by the right reverend Father and faithfull ſervant of CHRIST IESUS, <hi>Martin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> newly tranſlated out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> into Engliſh, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> student.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Can there any good thing come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Come, and ſee. <bibl>IOHN 1.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Anno Dom</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5429:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5429:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Coeleſtiall Chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der, <hi>W. W.</hi> wiſheth grace, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and peace, with a true and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowledge of our onely Lord omniſufficient Saviour and Redeemer CHRIST IESVS.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Doe offer and preſent vnto thee (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) heere publiſhed in Print, this little Treatiſe, firſt written by that famous and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learned Doctor in CHRISTS Schoole <hi>Martin Luther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſtotle ſaith that a goode thing, the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon it is made, the better it is.</note> in the Germane or Duche tongue, for his owne Countrey-men: after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards tranſlated into Latine, by a learned man, named <hi>Iuſtus Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> that it might bee common to noe then it was before: now alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough plainly, yet faithfully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urned into Engliſh, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ite and commoditie of this our I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrael,
<pb facs="tcp:5429:3"/> by one most studiouſly care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and zealouſly deſirous of thy profite. This excellent Preface will leade thee as a Lanterne of light to the better vnderstanding of that moſt precious,<note place="margin">The vſe of this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note> most fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and profitable Epiſtle of S. Paul to the <hi>Romans,</hi> which when thou canst well and wiſely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, firſt it will make thee rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy armed, well furniſhed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed to withſtand &amp; anſwear all the popiſh Romaniſts (GODS greateſt adverſaries, and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to his Gospell) who stoutlie maintaine and defend that mans workes doe merite and deſerue ſalvation, and ſo preſent vs juſt and righteous before GOD: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly it will teach thee a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian life &amp; converſation: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly how thou oughteſt to bring forth the worthie fruits of Faith
<pb facs="tcp:5429:3"/> which alone doth justifie vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, becauſe it is (as it were) the hand whereby wee apprehend and take hold fast of the merits of Chriſts bleſſed Paſſion to be ours Other branches of doctrine and manners there be in that notable Epiſtle good ſtore. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſe this prologue, and then it will lighten thy vnderſtanding verie much in this weighty matter of our ſalvation, in this chiefe and principall poynt of Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: to wit, whether wee bee juſtified by the works of the Law, or by the mercie of God only, for the mediation of his Sonne, who was made a ſlaine ſacrifice vpon the Croſſe for vs most wretched and miſerable ſinners. After that thou doeſt fully and perfitlie attaine to the true meaning of it, I doubt not but thou wilt (by the
<pb facs="tcp:5429:4"/> helpe of Gods holy Spirit working mightily in thee) perſevere and continue faithfull vnto the ende in this doctrine of faith taught heereby the Apoſtle.<note place="margin">Tim 1.19</note> Onely bee strong in the LORD, fight a gud fight, keeping faith and a good conſcience: then ſurelie this god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doctrine will prepare thy heart in a ſtrong defence, that the fiery darts of the Divels Ministers by errours and falſhood ſhall not wounde thee. Wherefore (gentle Reader) vſe this Introduction to thy comfort &amp; commoditie: Read and regard it, and giue God the glorie, who bee praiſed for ever and ever. Amen. Farewell in the Lord, and pray for me, as I daylie doe for thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epheſ. 2. v. 8. &amp; 9. By grace are yee ſaved through faith, and that not of your ſelves. For it is the gift of God, &amp; commeth not of workes: leaſt any man ſhould boaſt himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5429:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Methodicall Preface prefixed before the Epiſtle</hi> of S. Paul to the Romans, written by Martin Luther: and Engliſhed by W. W.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing that this Epiſtle of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> written vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> is the Methode of the whole Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the moſt abſolute Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome or Abridgement of the new Teſtament, that is, of the Goſpell (which verily alone it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth briefly and moſt purelie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et out vnto vs) I account it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orthie not onely of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ians to be knowne from their
<pb facs="tcp:5429:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> childhood,<note place="margin">The excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie of this Epiſtle</note> yea &amp; learned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the booke, word by word: but alſo (being by daylie and continuall meditation as it were chewed and concocted) even as well diſgeſted meate to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend and enter into our inner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt bowels. This Epiſtle is ſuch a rich treaſurie of ſpiritual wealth, and as it were a moſt plentifull <hi>Copiae Cornu,</hi> that hee that readeth it a thouſand times ſhall alwayes meete with ſome new thing not perceived be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. In ſo much that the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this Epiſtle is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable of all other, becauſe it doth, as it were aſcend higher in the doctrine of holy things, in the knowledge of Chriſt in learning the nature of faith, and in the knowledge of all ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>al affections: yea, the more it is
<pb facs="tcp:5429:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>andled, the greater it groweth more pleaſant and delightfull, more precious and plenteous it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>howeth and ſeemeth then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore. Wherefore I thought it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>abour well beſtowed, if (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that meaſure of grace which I haue received of God) I might put to my helping hand, and by this briefe Preface prepare an entrie into it: to the end that it might more eaſilie and plainlie bee read and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of al. Chiefely know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that this Epiſtle (which one alone ought to bee accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Index</hi> and Methode of all the Scriptures) hath beene ſo obſcured and darkened by certaine mens fooliſh Comen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries Gloſes, and vaine ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that verie few Writers in many ages paſt haue perceiued
<pb facs="tcp:5429:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> the drift, ſcope, meaning, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> intention of the Apoſtle, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> notwithinding of it ſelf is moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eaſie and plaine.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all we muſt diligent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſearch out &amp; labour to know the nature of words, and figu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ratiue ſpeaches which the A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſtle vſeth. And before al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things we muſt learne to know what S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> meaneth by theſe and ſuch like words: <hi>The Law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sinne, Grace, Faith, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Fleſh, Spirit, &amp;c</hi> Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thogh thou read diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thou looſeth all thy labour.</p>
            <p>This word <hi>Law,</hi> muſt not heere bee taken after the vſual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> manner of the Philoſophers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Law what it is, and how it is to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood.</note> or according to common reaſon: namely, to be defined a doctrine which teacheth men what to doe, and what to leaue vndone,
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5429:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ternall worke for the moſt part will breake out at length, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough it be for a time diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: this oftentimes followeth in ſuch hypocrits. Wherefore (as he ſaith) thou which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt another, teacheſt not thy ſelfe, that is, thou art ignorant thy ſelfe what thou teacheſt, becauſe thou art ignorant of the meaning of the law, how that it is not ſatisfied but with the inward affection and motion of the heart. The Law being done in the outward worke onely, is ſo farre from juſtifying, that it rather increaſeth and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteh our ſinne,<note place="margin">The Law encreaſeth ſinne</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in the 5. chapter of this Epiſtle Wherefore the better thou vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeſt the Law, the leſſe thou loveſt the law: becauſe it doth exact and requyre of thee
<pb facs="tcp:5429:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo many things quyte contrary to thy affections, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther repugnant to thy nature. Heerevpon it is that in the 7. chap. hee ſaith: The law is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall: as if hee ſhould ſay, If the law were carnall or morall doctrine onely, then it would bee ſatisfied by the externall worke. But ſeeing that now it is ſpirituall, that is, requyring the affect and ſpirit: it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that no man can fulfill it, vnleſſe hee doeth thoſe things which the law commandeth, with a chearefull heart, with a certaine ardent fervencie of minde, and with all his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Such a new heart, and ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ervent and chearefull affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the heart, thou canſt not obtaine of thine owne ſtrength, or by thine owne merites: but
<pb facs="tcp:5429:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nely by the operation and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ret inſtinct of the holie Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>For it is the Spirit of GOD <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nely that giues a new heart, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd that makes a man ſpiritual: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſo being made ſpirituall, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay loue the law which is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ituall, and may fulfill it, not for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare, or loue of commoditie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut with a chearefull and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing heart, and that hee may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aried violently (as it wer with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> certaine force) to doe thoſe things which the law comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth, freely, and of his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. So is that ſaying to bee vnderſtood. The Law is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, that is, the Law is not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled but by the Spirit, but by a heart renued by the Spirit. Therefore where there is not that renovation of the heart by the ſpirit, there remaineth that
<pb facs="tcp:5429:8"/> grieuous hatred of the law (which law nevertheleſſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelfe is juſt, holy, and good) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> farre is it from fulfilling it.</p>
            <p>Wherefore accuſtome an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> acquaynt thy ſelfe with thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Phraſe and manner of ſpeakin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which the Apoſtle heere vſeth It is one thing to do the work of the law, and another thing to fulfill the law. For it is a worke of the law when with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out grace,<note place="margin">1. Workes of the Law.</note> without the Spirit wee beginne to worke well, and when wee labour to fulfill the law by our owne proper ſtrength and power of our free will. But ſeeing that there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes remaineth in the heart certaine ſervile feare and a moſt deadly hatred of the law, ſure it is that ſuch workes are ſinne and haynous factes againſt the
<pb facs="tcp:5429:8"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w, and ſo doe not pleaſe God. the Apoſtle ſaith in the 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hapter: By the workes of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w ſhall no fleſh bee juſtified his ſight. Heere therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e may know and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ge how the Sophiſters and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oole doctors are farre wide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m the truth, who teach and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irme this wicked and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emous aſſertion: that by our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orkes wee may prepare the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay vnto grace. But how can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>repare for my ſelfe away to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace by that worke which <hi>I</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with a ſtubborne, froward, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d vntoward heart, and with repugnant affection: How <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n that worke bee acceptable God which I doe not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>gly but with great griefe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eart, yea with extreme hatred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the law.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5429:9"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> To fulfill the law, is to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe things which the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> commandeth with a cheereſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and willing heart,<note place="margin">Fulfilling of the law.</note> that is, free and of thine own accorde to li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnto God, and to worke we though there were no law all.</p>
            <p>Such a cherefulneſſe, read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, willingneſſe, and arde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> affection, cannot come int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our hearts but by the quickning Spirit and his liuely impulſion and agitations in our heart, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Apoſtle ſayeth in the 5 Chapter. Now the Spirit is g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven onely by faith in IESU<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> CHRIST, as the Apoſtle ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the beginning. Faith com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth through the hearing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Ghoſpell, through whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> word Chriſt is preached vnt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs, to haue died, to haue been<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5429:9"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ried, and to haue riſen againe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om death for vs, as hee ſaith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the 3. 4. and 10. Chapters. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore our whole juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on is of GOD: Faith alſo and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Spirit are of GOD: they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me not of our ſelves. Where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re let vs conclude that Faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one juſtifieth and that Faith one fulfilleth the Law. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith through the merite of CHRIST obtaineth the holie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pirit, which Spirit doth make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s new hearts, doth exhilarate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, doth excite and inflame our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eart that it may doe thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hings willingly of loue which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he law commandeth, and ſo at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he laſt good workes in deede <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe proceede freely from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith which worketh ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ily, and which is ſo liuely in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur hearts. This is the meaning
<pb facs="tcp:5429:10"/> of the third Chapter. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whereas hee had vtterly da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned the workes of the law, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> might haue ſeemed to haue d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> anulled and aboliſhed the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the teaching the doctrine faith, hee preventeth that o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jection in theſe words. We d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not (ſayth he) deſtroy the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but rather eſtabliſh it. That wee teach how the law m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truely bee fulfilled by faith. by beleeving in CHRIST IE<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>SVS.</p>
            <p>Now it remaineth that we ſhew how this word <hi>(Sinne)</hi> taken in the Scriptures.<note place="margin">2 what</note> 
               <hi>Sin n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in the Scriptures ſignifieth no onely the externall worke: b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that whole force and natiue o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peration incredulitie, as tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wickedneſſe which wee hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by lineall deſcent (as it were
<pb facs="tcp:5429:10"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om our great Graundfather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de Adam, which even vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntly carrieth vs headlong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſinne, namely that wicked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eart and all our reaſon, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> (yea even his beſt and chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt) his ſtrength and power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herwith we can doe nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e but ſinne: ſo that then wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſaid to commit ſinne, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the efficacy of this originall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nne (as with a certaine violent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rce) wee are caried headlong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o doe evill. There is no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ard ſinne done but firſt by his naturall force and impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on a man is wholly and with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l his affection caryed roundly way to ſinning. The Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd God himſelfe, when they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake of ſin, they haue reſpect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto this wickedneſſe of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earts, vnto this naturall incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<pb facs="tcp:5429:11"/> that is, this vice of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> credulitie, as to the fountai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of all other ſins. Lyke as the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore Faith alone doth juſtify &amp; alone doth obtaine the Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit and pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to fulfill the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; to doe tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> workes in de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which are one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood: ſo one incredultitie a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nbeleefe ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth ſin, and exciteth and kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth the fleſh to ſinne, and commit evill workes, as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſee it happened to Adam a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Eue in Paradiſe. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sinne is principaly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>med vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>efe</note>Wherefore CHRIST alſo the Goſpell calleth onely a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> chiefly incredulitie, ſin. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1 The Spirit (ſaith hee) ſhall r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proue the world of ſinne, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe they haue not beleeved mee. Thoſe workes which truly good, even as good frui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cannot proceed and ſpring b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5429:11"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f a good tree, that is, of faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orking in the heart: as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ariewiſe evill fruite can not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome but from an evill tree, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat is, incredulitie of the hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Therefore this wickedneſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd incredulitie of the heart, is very where in the Scriptures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lled the head of the Serpent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d of the old Dragon,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as to be broken by that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſeede of the woman, namely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>HRIST.</p>
            <p>But now to proceed: As con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erning theſe two words <hi>grace</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>gift,</hi> they differ thus,<note place="margin">Grace what it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Grace</hi> the favour, mercy, and free <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood will and benevolence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>OD towards vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gift</hi> is the holy Spirit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lfe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> whom God doth ſend in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> their hearts whom hee hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ken mercy vpon,<note place="margin">Gyft what it is</note> and whom
<pb facs="tcp:5429:12"/> he favoureth; as very well ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peareth in the 5 chap. wher he diſtinguiſhes gift fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace Althogh now we haue not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fulnes of this gift or of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit (becauſe in this life ther wil alwayes remaine in vs re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nants of ſin which fight again the Spirlt, as the Apoſtle ſayt in the 7 chap. and the 3 Galat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as alſo <hi>Moſes</hi> ſayeth in the 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gen. that there will bee a con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flict betwixt the ſeede of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> woman and the ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pent) yet grace worketh this i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs that the reliques of ſin ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not bee imputed vnto vs: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that we ſhall be reputed an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accounted before God as me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fully and perfitly juſt. Neithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is the grace and favour of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo imperfitely beſtowed vpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs: as we ſaid the gift was. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5429:12"/> God rather doth love and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace vs with a full favour and a right perfite goode will for Chriſts ſake, who is our medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, earneſt penny and the firſt fruits of the Spirit. Therefore though remnants of ſinne dayly doe gliſter and ſhine in vs: yet nevertheleſſe we are juſt before God, and ſin is not imputed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs throgh faith, which day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ſtriveth and wageth warre againſt the fleſh.</p>
            <p>So then you may vnderſtand that place in the 7 chap. where the Apoſtle, though he was ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in the Spirite, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edgeth himſelf yet to bee a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: and yet notwithſtanding hee ſaith in the 8 chap. There is now no condemnation to theſe which are in Chriſt Ieſus. As many therfore of vs as are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb facs="tcp:5429:13"/> through faith in Chriſt, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are both ſinners and juſt. Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners by reaſon of the imperfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mortification of our fleſh, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for that in this life (the relique of ſin remaining in vs) we can not haue or attaine the fulneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Spirit. Firſt becauſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue throgh faith the firſt fruit and earneſt of the Spirit: ſo tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for our faith in Chriſt, God fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therly favouring vs, doth no impute vnto vs that ſin whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> remaineth in our fleſh: neithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doth judge vs vntill that ſinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by death bee quyte broken, ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed, and aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5. Faith what it is.</note>But now let vs ſpeake ſome what of faith. Faith is not a cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine colde opinion or a wan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dring cogitation of a mans mynde, ſuch a one as any man (hearing the hiſtorie of the
<pb facs="tcp:5429:13"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſpell) may fooliſhly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne himſelfe to haue.</p>
            <p>For certaine men (hearing any things preached of faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſeeing that they can diſpute any things of faith and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſt, and yet for all that by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at knowledge, cogitation, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igent meditation, perceiue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>emſelues not to bee foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th incited to do gud works) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> into that wicked and impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s error, that they ſtoutly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man to be juſtified by faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n: but that alſo works are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yred. theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> indeed hearing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Goſpel, faine to themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ertaine opinion, and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lve in their mindes certaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d cogitations of Chriſt, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g then that faith is nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the dreame of their owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd and thoſe vaine cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb facs="tcp:5429:14"/> And theſe men now and then boult out theſe excellent ſpeeches.<note place="margin">A fayned faith</note> O (ſay they) if faith onely juſtifieth them, I pray you what ſay you to this? Behold, I haue heard the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell preached; I remember the hiſtory of Chriſt: Loe, I belieue and yet am not juſtified. True it is, for becauſe this thy faith is nothing but thy owne bare and naked imagination and cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of faith which doth not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novate thy hart, &amp; which doth move thee nothing at all, there followeth no newneſſe of life, no works of faith.</p>
            <p>But a true faith is the worke of God whereby wee are rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and borne anew by his Spirit. Iohn I chap: whereby alſo our old Adam is quelled, &amp; we being wholly tranſ-formed,
<pb facs="tcp:5429:14"/> wee are made (as the Apoſtle ſaith) new creatures to Chriſt, the holye Ghoſt being the life, and government of our hearts. Wherfore faith is ſuch an effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, lively,<note place="margin">Faith is lively and not idle.</note> quick and mighty operation in our heart, that it cannot bee idle, but muſt needs breake out, and ſhew it ſelfe by good works</p>
            <p>Neither doth he that hath this faith care greatly whether good works be commanded or no? For though there were no law at all, yet by this liuely impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion working in his heart, he is of his owne accord forced and caried to work true and godly Chriſtian works.</p>
            <p>Hee that doeth not his good works of ſuch a lively affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the heart, is wholly in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe, &amp; a ſtranger and aliant
<pb facs="tcp:5429:15"/> from the faith, as many of theſe be which in ſchooles diſpute &amp; jangle much of Faith and good workes, not knowing what they ſpeake, or what they hold and affirme.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A true de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of Faith.</note>Faith therefore is a conſtant truſt and a ſure confidence of the mercie of God towards vs, which is lively, and worketh mightily in our hearts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee commit our ſelves wholly to God, caſting all our care vpon him: leaning and truſting aſſuredly to this Faith, wee ate not affrayde to die a thouſand times. For this ſo bold an aſſurance of the mercie and favour of God doth make our hearts merry, glad, and light: doth alſo erect, raiſe, and even raviſh vs with moſt ſweet mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and affections towardes
<pb facs="tcp:5429:15"/> God: yea and doth ſo embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the heart of the true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer, that truſting to haue God on his ſide, hee is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayde to oppoſe himſelf alone againſt all creatures. But it is the Spirit of GOD which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth vs this heroicall heart and ſtout ſtomacke through faith, which working effectually in our hearts, doth incyte and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame vs to doe good. Now we haue this chearefull towardnes and forwardneſſe, to the end that we might be moſt prompt and ready willingly and of our owne accorde to doe, tolerate, and ſuffer all things, whereby wee may bee obedient to ſo gentle and favourable a father, who through Chriſt hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched vs with ſo great aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of his graces. It can not
<pb facs="tcp:5429:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> poſſiblie bee but that in whom ſoever this efficacy and lyfe of fayth is, it ſhould dayly worke, fructifie, and giue increaſe to God.<note place="margin">A liuely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon.</note> Even as it is vnpoſſible that a fire being kindled and flaming ſhould not giue light and caſt foorth brightneſſe, wherfore watch thou and take heed that thou doe not beleeue either thine owne vaine ſonges and ſounds of faith,<note place="margin">Fancyes</note> thine own fooliſh imaginations, or the vayne trifling ſtuffe of Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.<note place="margin">Blynd Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note> For theſe Sophiſters haue neither wit nor wiſdome. They are belly beaſtes borne onely to thoſe feaſts of ſchooles. But pray thou vnto God (who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth by his worde that light ſhould ſhine out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) that hee would ſhyne brightly in thine heart, &amp; that
<pb facs="tcp:5429:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> hee would create a true Faith in thee: otherwiſe thou ſhall never beleeue truely, though for the ſpace of a thouſand yeares thou diddeſt labour and ſtudy about ſuch cogitations &amp; imaginations, either of a faith heretofore gotten, or heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be ſought for.<note place="margin">Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> This faith now is, that true juſtice which the Apoſtle calleth the juſtice and righteouſneſſe of God, that is, which onely is of force a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaylable and can ſtand before God: becauſe it is the meere gift of God. And this faith doth transforme the whole man and makes him ſuch a one, that (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that common defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of civill juſtice) he is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to giue and render to everie one that which is due to him. For ſeeing by that faith we are
<pb facs="tcp:5429:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> juſtified and indued with the love of the lawe of God, then ſurely we ſo (magnifying God and the law) doe giue that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnto God which is due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. Alſo ſeing by that faith wee doe belieue firmely that we are juſtified freely, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled vnto GOD through Chriſt, who every where is ready to ſaue vs, then by courſe we ſerve for our neighbour, &amp; ſo againe render &amp; attribute to everie man that which is his. This righteouſnes of the heart we cannot obtaine by any inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of our owne free will, or by our ſtrength and merits. For as no man can ſee that lively o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, that is, faith of our hearts, but onely GOD: ſo no man can repell from himſelfe that wickedneſſe and incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb facs="tcp:5429:17"/> of the heart but onely by grace and the Spirit of God: ſo farre we are from being able to deliver our ſelves from ſinnes by our own power. Therefore though workes doe ſeeme to ſhow gallantly and gloriouſly: yet notwithſtanding whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is not of faith, is hypocriſie and ſinne.</p>
            <p>Now as concerning fleſh &amp; ſpirit which often are vſed in this Epiſtle: you muſt not take fleſh to be (after the common manner) the deſires and luſts of the fleſh only, neither muſt you call the ſpirit only theſe things which are done ſpiritually in the inward corners of the hart. For the Apoſtle S. Paul (as alſo Chriſt himſelf in the 3 chap. of <hi>Iohn</hi> doe call fleſh,<note place="margin">6. Fleſh wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is.</note> whatſoever is borne of the fleſh, that is, the
<pb facs="tcp:5429:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> whole man body and ſoule, all mans reaſon wholy with all his chiefeſt and beſt powers: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that all theſe thinges doe ſavour of nothing but fleſh, &amp; ſeeke after nothing but fleſhly things. Wherefore thou ſhall call al thoſe works fleſh, which ſeeme to bee good, and make a beautifull ſhow of holy works, and yet are done without the grace and working of the holy Spirit of GOD in the heart. Which thing is plaine and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the 5 chap. to the Gal. where Paul reckoneth &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth hereſies amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the fruits of the fleſh. And in the 7 chap. to the Romans he ſaith, that the law is made weake, by reaſon of the fleſh, which thing ought to be meant not only of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſte luſts of the fleſh, but alſo
<pb facs="tcp:5429:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the whole maſſe of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on and wickedneſſe: yea briefly and chiefly of incredulitie, or vnbeliefe,<note place="margin">Incredulity the ground of al ſinnes</note> which is the moſte ſecreet and chiefe ſinne of all.</p>
            <p>Contrarywiſe,<note place="margin">7. Spirit what it is.</note> thou ſhalt call the Spirit thoſe ſpirituall things, even thoſe externall workes which proceede from a ſpiritual man, or from a heart innovated and made newe by the holy ſpirit. That waſhing of the feete which Chriſt did to his Diſciples, though it was an outward worke, yet it was ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>Peters fiſhing, to which hee returned being now juſtified in the ſpirit, was alſo ſpirituall. Therefore that is fleſh, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever a man doth, ſeeking and ſavoring only carnall and fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things. And that is Spirit,
<pb facs="tcp:5429:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> whatſoever is done within or without, wherewith a man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing faith and Charity, doth ſeeke ſpirituall things. Vnleſſe wee take theſe words in this ſenſe, wee ſhall neither vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this Epiſtle of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul, nor any other bookes of the divyne Scriptures. Therefore whether it bee <hi>Ierome,</hi> or <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine,</hi> or <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> or <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen:</hi> briefly what writers ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they bee that vſe theſe words otherwiſe, let not the authoritie of men moue thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing at all, but rather flee from them al as from the plague and peſtilence. But now let vs come to handle the Epiſtle it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A godly in ſtruction for readers</note>Seeing therefore it is the duety and office of an Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt or preacher of glad tydings,
<pb facs="tcp:5429:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> firſt of all to preach the Law and to ſhew how that all men (which are without the circuit and compaſſe of grace and faith in Chriſt) are the ſonnes and children of wrath, are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and can doe nothing but ſinne, that ſo they acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their miſerie and wretched<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe with an humble and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heart, might thirſt after grace, the Apoſtle S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul in in this firſt Chapter doeth firſt of all finde fault with the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.</note> and checketh and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buketh thoſe groſſe ſins which aptly &amp; plainly were knowne to be manifeſt offences,<note place="margin">The ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of S. Pauls doctrine.</note> as were the Idolatry and ſuch groſſe ſinnes of the Gentiles: as alſo are of thoſe men which at this day being ignorant of GOD, voyde of grace, and without
<pb facs="tcp:5429:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Spirit, doe liue in blindnes and darkneſſe. The wrath of God is revealed by the Goſpel (ſaith the Apoſtle) from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven againſt al vngodlineſſe and vnrighteouſneſſe of men which withhold the truth in vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. For though man might know by the Creatures that there was a God: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his nature is evill and wicked, inſomuch that it doth not glorifie him nor giue him thankes, but being blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, doth alwayes giue over it ſelfe to worſe and worſe, vntil they doe not onely commit I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie and al kind of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. but alſo favour them that doe them, and giue their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and agreement to thoſe which commit ſuch things.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.</note>In the ſecond Chap. he doth
<pb facs="tcp:5429:20"/> more at large ſhew that even theſe litle holy ones, and thoſe glorious hypocrites (as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Iewes then,<note place="margin">The Iewes as ill, or worſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners than the Gentils</note> and now in theſe dayes all the Iuſticiaries which go about by their owne ſtrength and power to fulfil the lawe) are alſo ſinners, who by dooing outwardly the goode works of the law: notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding inwardly nouriſhing that griefe of their heart, doe hate the law.</p>
            <p>And theſe (as right hypocrits commonly vſe to doe) are very quick to condemne other men, counting themſelves holy and pure, when as they are full of malice and envy, fraud, deceit, &amp; all kinde of filthineſſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneſſe, as Chriſt ſayeth Mat. 23. And theſe are they which faining themſelves holye, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne
<pb facs="tcp:5429:21"/> and deſpiſe in very deed the great goodneſſe of God, &amp; according to the hardneſſe of their hearts, heape and treaſure vp to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves wrath, againſt the day of wrath. <hi>Paul</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as a true Evangeliſt firſt of all preacheth the Law,<note place="margin">All are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all men alike to be ſinners and denuncing to all the wrath of God. Wherefore they who marke well, by the power of their owne nature or free-will, are ſo farre from being any bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than thoſe groſſe and open ſinners mentioned in the firſt Chapter: that the Apoſtle cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them obſtinate, ſtubborne, men that cannot repent, aliants and ſtrangers.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap,</hi> 3.</note>In the third Chap. hee decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth that both the Iewes and the Gentiles are alyke ſinners
<pb facs="tcp:5429:21"/> before God:<note place="margin">Difference betwixt both Iewe and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile.</note> notwithſtanding that the Iewes are preferred &amp; excell the Gentiles in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, namely, for that the pormiſes of God did belong to them, &amp; alſo for that the words and Oracles of God were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto them. And thogh ſome of the Iewes did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, yet for all that their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe made not the faithfull trueth of Gods promiſes vaine, voyde, or without effect: and to prove this, he alledgeth that place of the 51. Pſalme: as it is written (ſaith hee) that thou mighteſt bee juſtified in thy wordes, and overcome when thou art judged. After this hee returneth to his cauſe and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and proveth by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures, that all are equallie ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners without any exception, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:5429:22"/> that no man is juſtified by the workes of the law: but that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the lawe commeth the knowledge of ſinne. Finally he teacheth the true &amp; right ways of righteouſnes and ſalvation. All (ſaith hee) haue ſinned,<note place="margin">The hye way to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is by fayth in Chriſt.</note> and are deſtitute and deprived o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the glorie of God: but they are juſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Chriſt Ieſus, whom GOD hath ſet foorth to bee a recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation through faith in his blood. And a little before: But now (ſaith hee) is the rigteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of GOD made manifeſt without the law, being appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the teſtimonie and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, to wit, the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, by the faith of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt vnto all and vpon al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5429:22"/> that beleeue. So then the lawe is eſtabliſhed through faith, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though workes and glorying in the workes of the law are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by faith.</p>
            <p>Seeing therfore in the three former Chapters, hee hath taught, that all men are ſinners: &amp; alſo ſheweth that only faith in Chriſt, is the way vnto righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and meanes to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.</note> by and by in this fourth Chap. he anſwereth to certaine objections and cauils. As for the moſt part, when Chriſt or faith is taught (that is, that our works are nothing, that wee are onely juſtified by faith) ſtreight wayes certaine Iuſticiaries object: If faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone doth juſtifie, then we muſt ceaſe altogether to doe good workes, then good works are
<pb facs="tcp:5429:23"/> to be omitted and left vndone. The Apoſtle anſwereth, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the example of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham: <hi>What ſhall wee ſay then, that Abraham our Father hath hath found concerning the fleſh? Did hee merite nothing at all by his workes?</hi> He concludeth, that Abraham was juſtified onely by faith without any workes, inſomuch that the Scripture ſaith, that Abraham (before he was circumciſed) beleeved GOD, and it was counted and reputed vnto him for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.6. If therefore the worke of circumciſion which GOD commaunded (which was a precious worke of obedience) profited Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham nothing to juſtification, then it is moſt ſure &amp; certaine, that there is none other worke
<pb facs="tcp:5429:23"/> which is available to juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">An apt ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude.</note> But as circumciſion being an outward ſigne, was vnto Abraham a ſeale of his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes by faith: ſo good works are onely an externall ſigne, which doth not juſtifie, but which doth ſignifie vnto men, that a man is inwardly juſtified before God, and they doe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and approue as certaine ſignes and fruits, that liuelie faith, which worketh in the heart. By this, as by the moſt graue, weighty, and authentik example, the Apoſtle doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, &amp; build out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures his doctrine of faith de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered out, and taught in the third Chapter. Furthermore, the Apoſtle allegeth the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of David in the 32. Pſal. to proue this matter. Alſo in
<pb facs="tcp:5429:24"/> moſt plaine words hee affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that a man is juſtified by the imputation of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, without works: althogh (as I haue ſaid before) workes doe follow thoſe that are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Faith. Moreover hee dilateth and amplifieth the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample againſt all other workes of the lawe, inferring that the Iewes are not therfore ſtraight way the true heires of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, becauſe their ſtocke and pedigrue is derived from the circumciſed Abraham, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they received the lawe, vnleſſe they tread and follow the ſteps of ſaith, and beleeving in Chriſt, imitate the faith of Abraham: ſpecially and chiefly, ſeeing that Abraham before the law (whether it were of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or of the circumciſion) was
<pb facs="tcp:5429:24"/> juſtified onely by faith, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the father of many nations, that is, of all beleevers. Finally hee concludeth thus: Seeing that the lawe cannot giue that effectuall working, whereby it may willingly and chearefully be ſatisfied: alſo ſeeing that the grudging and murmuring ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp by the law, abideth and remaineth in vs, and diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth &amp; taketh it grievouſly that there ſhould bee any poſitiue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aw ſet downe for her, I ſay that this hatred againſt the law, and the law giver God himſelfe ſtil continuing, it cannot bee that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he workes of the law ſhould pleaſe God: Nay rather ſeeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey proceed from a heart that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bhorreth the ſawe and God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey are nothing elſe but ſinne. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd doe alwayes incenſe and
<pb facs="tcp:5429:25"/> kindle the indignation &amp; wrath of God. Wherefore Faith only doth obtaine the bleſſing and grace promiſed to Abraham. Now it is not written for him onely, but alſo for vs (as Paul ſaith in the latter ende of this Chapter) the faith might alſo bee imputed and reckened to vs for righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>In the fifth Chapter, hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth of workes, and of the fruits of faith which bee theſe: peace, joy of conſcience, loue towards GOD and our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: a profitable, couragious &amp; bold confidence: and a ſtoute and manfull perſeverance and pacient in tribulations and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, for ſtreight way theſe fruits follow, whereſoever this true faith is in the heart. Surely that moſt excellent riches, and
<pb facs="tcp:5429:25"/> aboundant wealth of the grace of God offered, and exhibited to vs in Chriſt (whom GOD would haue dye for vs, when wee were as yet weaklings, yea enemies to God) if ſo bee, by faith it be knowne &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged of vs in our hearts, it cannot but inflame vs, and mak vs ſtrong and able to doe moſt willingly, cherefully, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, all thoſe things which we know will pleaſe this our moſt gentle Father. Therefore the chiefe ſentence, drift and ſcope of this Epiſtle ſtands ſtedfaſt and ſure, namely, that by fayth alone wee are juſtified, without workes, and yet for all that good workes are not condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. For thoſe workes that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and truely may be called good, and thoſe good fruits doe
<pb facs="tcp:5429:26"/> follow faith, and whereſoever faith is, it cannot chooſe but worke: Like as the flame can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but giue good light. Of theſe that be truly good works the Iuſticiaries (who have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo riſe in their mouths, as works, works, works) knowe nothing at all: They doe but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly jmagine in themſelves cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain cold works, which becaus they haue no ſparke of faith in them, are voyde of all ſpirituall affections: as joy, peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and that bold truſt and aſſurance in God and are rotten fruits of a rotten tree. After this the Apoſtle maketh a pleaſant digreſſion, ſhewing how ſin &amp; righteouſneſſe, alſo how death &amp; life came vpon vs. And there he compareth theſe two, Adam and Chriſt. Wherefore he rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneth
<pb facs="tcp:5429:26"/> thus:<note place="margin">The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> It was therefore needfull and neceſſarie, that Chriſt ſhould bee ſent, who ſhould make his righteouſneſſe to be ours, by the new birth or regeneration in faith &amp; the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, even as the old man Adam by propagation left vs his ſinne through that old generation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fleſh. Againe, by this argument aaother propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſurely grounded, namely, that no man by his own ſtrenth &amp; power is able to deliver him ſelf from ſin, or to juſtifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. For it was not in our choiſe to be borne, or not to be borne of the old Adam, &amp; according to the fleſh, which by other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments is evident, and cleare enough. For if the law of God (which ſurly, if any other thing in the world might haue juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb facs="tcp:5429:27"/> ought to haue prevailed and availed for righteouſnes) doth not only not juſtifie, but rather increaſeth &amp; augmenteth ſinne in vs, namely, that grudging &amp; fretting of our nature, dayly ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macking &amp; murmuring at God: yea the more it doth preſſe vs, the more it ſtirreth vp ſinne in our nature,<note place="margin">Nitimur in vetitum ſemper cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> negata.</note> which goeth againſt all whatſoever is forbidden. Therefore the more perfitly we know the law the more miſery we behold in our ſelves, and we ſee the better how that wee have more need of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.</note>In the 6 chap. hee handleth that great and chiefe worke of faith, to wit, the warfare &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flict of Chriſtians betwixt the fleſh &amp; the ſpirit.<note place="margin">The war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of Chriſtians.</note> For the fleſh fighteth againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit wageth warre againſt the
<pb facs="tcp:5429:27"/> fleſh, to the end that the deſires of the fleſh, &amp; reliques of ſinne, which remaine in vs after iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, might be quite ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, quelled, &amp; quenched in vs.</p>
            <p>And in this chap. the Apoſt. teacheth, that we are not ſo ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified &amp; freed from ſin by faith that ſin is quite taken away, and altogether aboliſhed in vs:<note place="margin">Reliques of ſinne.</note> but that the reliques of ſinne as yet remaine in vs. Nevertheles theſe remnants of ſinne are not laid to our charge, by reaſon of faith, which continually wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les with the deſires of the fleſh. wherfore as yet, becaus we liue in the fleſh, that ſtrife &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat indureth in vs, &amp; they that are already juſtified haue enogh to doe, &amp; haue labour enough to turne them vnto: yea all their lifetime they maye toyle vntill
<pb facs="tcp:5429:28"/> they ſweat againe, by indevour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to tame their fleſhe, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the luſts of it, &amp; to make it ſubject vnto the Spirit.<note place="margin">Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> And by that mortification of our fleſh, &amp; newnes of our ſpiritual life, we expreſſe the Death and the Reſurrection of Chriſt, as alſo that ſigne of mortification in Baptiſme, which doth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and repreſent vnto vs no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, but this continuall mortification of the fleſh, and dayly vivification &amp; quickning of the ſpirit. For Baptiſme, that is this mortification doth work in vs ſo long, vntill ſin being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed and abandoned by the death of our bodies, wee riſe in our bodyes with Chriſt, and raigne with him for evermore.</p>
            <p>And this thing (namely, the dayly mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our fleſh)
<pb facs="tcp:5429:28"/> we may performe, becauſe we are not vnder the law: but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der grace. Now what it is, not to bee vnder the law,<note place="margin">What it is, not to bee vnder the Law.</note> muſt not bee ſo vnderſtood, as though it were lawfull for vs to do what wee liſt: but not to bee vnder the law is this, that our hearts are ſo made new by the ſpirit, through faith, that freely, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and of our owne accord, wee may doe that which the lawe requyres, though there were no lawe at all. For grace doth endue vs with the loue of the law. Wherefore we being juſtified, haue no more the law againſt vs, but agreeing with vs. To bee vnder the law,<note place="margin">What it is to be vnder the Law.</note> is to worke without grace, and not to bee able to fulfill the lawe, where there cannot chooſe but bee ſinne.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5429:29"/>
            <p>And this now at length is the true liberty and freedome from the law and ſin, of which the Apoſtle heere diſputeth, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven vnto the end of this Chap. As for this libertie it is ſuch, that wee may willingly from our hearts doe good without any exaction of the law. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a ſpirituall libertie which doth not take away the law: but giveth and imparteth a certaine power, and ſpirit to fulfill the law: namely, a chere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mynde, a ready will, and fervent deſire to worke well, whereby it doth then ſatisfie the law: inſomuch that it hath not any thing to exact at his hand, or to charge him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.<note place="margin">A fit &amp; apt ſimilitude.</note> Even as if thou were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to a certaine creditor of thine, &amp; didſt owe him a great
<pb facs="tcp:5429:29"/> ſumme of money, thou mighteſt after two wayes ſatisfie him, and ſo diſcharge the debt: Firſt by a free forgivenes of the debt, and cancelling of thy handwri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Secondly, by ſuretie of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother man, who will giue his faith and truth for thee, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to ſtand to the payment of all the foreſaid money, and ſo by his word and faith given for the obligation, wherewith thou waſt bound, may be blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and cancelled, as voyde, &amp; of none effect. Likewiſe Chriſt hath delivered vs from the law as from a creditor. Wherefore that libertie is not carnall, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by it is lawfull to do what thou wilt: but is altogether labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and paynefull, which wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly doth good workes: ſo that it needs not any exaction
<pb facs="tcp:5429:30"/> of the law.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.</note>In the ſeventh Chap. he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth this by a certaine ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of marriage, betweene the husband and the wife. For even as the woman if her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band be dead,<note place="margin">A ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ude to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>roue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>berty fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he law.</note> is delivered from the law of the man: not ſo freed that ſhee may not marry, but rather contrarie: now firſt of al ſhe is freed indeed and truely, that ſhee may marry another man, which ſhe could not doe before ſhe was deliuered from her former husband: ſo alſo our conſcience is dead to the lawe, as long as old Adam liveth in vs. But when this olde Adam is mortified by the ſpirit, there is then libertie for both parties, like as I haue ſaid there was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt man and wife: But the conſcience is not free, ſo that it
<pb facs="tcp:5429:30"/> cannot at all doe any worke: but rather ſo that now hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to cleaue vnto another, even vnto Chriſt, that it ſhould bring forth fruite vnto God.</p>
            <p>After this, hee doth at large explicate the nature of ſinne,<note place="margin">The natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of ſinne.</note> &amp; of the law: ſhewing the lawe to bee the force and power of ſinne, For the olde Adam or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, how much more it is preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed downe by the law, (which of his owne ſtrength hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not fulfill) ſo much the more it doth fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t and fume againſt it. And no maruell, ſeeing it can doe nothing of it ſelfe, but ſin. Therefore the law is vnto it a puniſhment, and death: not that the law is evill: but this is done through the fault of our owne nature, which taketh it grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly, that any good ſhould be
<pb facs="tcp:5429:31"/> exacted of it which ſhe cannot fulfill: not vnlike a ſickly weake man who is heavily diſpleaſed, if any man requyre of him to doe thoſe works, or that maine ſtrength which is in a ſound &amp; ſtrong man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The nature of the law.</note>Wherefore Paul heere in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth, that the law, the more exactly &amp; throghly it is known doth worke in vs nothing elſe, but this, that it doth the more ſhew our ſinne and increaſe it: by which it doth ſlay vs, and mak vs guiltie of eternall death and of the wrath of God. But of this matter no man can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute better than he whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience hath felt &amp; had triall of the terrour of the Law: whoſe conſcience hath felt that ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and quaking (as it were) the verie foundations of the
<pb facs="tcp:5429:31"/> earth, and who hath well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it at ſome time or other to haue cauſed a great tumult in his heart. Therefore we haue neede of a more effectuall and mightier force in our hearts to juſtifie vs, than the Law is. Truely they that haue not ſo knowne the law, they are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether blind, &amp; walk in this life in a certaine bolde confidence, thinking that they can fulfil the law by their works: not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering at all, how that the Law doeth imperiouſly require the whole heart, and all the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Wherfore theſe men behold not the end of the Lawe: onely they view the covered and hid face of <hi>Moſes</hi> without grace, who are like perpetually to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in their vaine works.</p>
            <p>After theſe matters, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb facs="tcp:5429:32"/> ſetteth forth,<note place="margin">The ſtrife twixt the fleſh &amp; the ſpirit, even in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate.</note> how the fleſh and the Spirit in one and the ſame man doth ſtrive and wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle together: &amp; hee exhibiteth himſelf vnto vs, as an example (though hee was juſtified.) Wheerby we might learne this mortification of the remnants of ſin. Now he calleth both the Spirit and the fleſh, a certaine law. <hi>I haue found</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a law in my members contrarie &amp; repugnant &amp;c.</hi> For like as the law of God doth vrge and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act thoſe things to bee done of vs, which God wold haue done ſo the law of the members or of the fleſh, doth incite and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell vs to carnall things, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the ſpirit. Againe, on the other ſide, the ſpirit doth labour mightily againſt the fleſh, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving vs to ſpiritual things. And
<pb facs="tcp:5429:32"/> this conflict &amp; combat dureth ſo long as wee are clothed with this fleſh. In this man the ſtrife is mightier and ſtronger: in that man more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe &amp; faint: in everie man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly as the ſpirit, or fleſh is in him, ſtronger or weaker: notwithſtanding one and the ſame man is that fleſh &amp; ſpirit, which ſo ſtrives and wreſtles with himſelfe, vntill (Sinne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quyte aboliſhed) hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſpirituall,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the 8 chap. he comforteth thoſe which fight ſo with their owne fleſh:<note place="margin">A comfort for the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> alſo hee declareth that the reliques of ſin can not hurt vs: that there is no conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to them that are in Ieſus Chriſt, which walke not after the fleſh, but according to the ſpirit. Furthermore, hee doeth
<pb facs="tcp:5429:33"/> explicate at large the nature of the fleſh &amp; ſpirit, ſhewing that the ſpirit is given to man onely by Chriſt. He that hath not the ſpirit of Chriſt (ſaith hee) the ſame man is none of his. Again, as many as are led by the ſpirit of God, they are the ſonnes of God. For it is the Spirit alone which doth innovate &amp; renew our hearts, which doeth make them ſpirituall, which doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage vs with ſweet and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving affects and motions: laſtly which doth giue teſtimonie &amp; beare witnes vnto our ſpirits, that we are the very ſonnes of God, teaching vs that wee (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thogh ſin doth boyle with rage within our fleſh) haue God for our Father, &amp; may account our ſelves his ſonnes, if ſo bee that we doe dayly by the ſpirit
<pb facs="tcp:5429:33"/> wreſtle againſt the fleſh.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe nothing is more profitable to the mortifying of the olde Adam the fleſh, than the croſſe, tribulation &amp; afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is, the Apoſtle doeth heere comfort vs in theſe tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, affirming that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit doth make interceſſion, and requeſt for vs with ſighes that cannot be vttered &amp; expreſſed: alſo that all the creatures, being ſubject to vanitie &amp; abuſe, doe even groane &amp; travell in paine together with vs, vntill this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of ſin be aboliſhed, and the glory of the ſonnes of God bee revealed. Thus wee ſee that theſe three laſt Chapters, doe vrge nothing ſo much, as this onely and chiefe worke of our faith, namely, the mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our olde Adam, which is
<pb facs="tcp:5429:34"/> the fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. 10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11</note>In the 9. 10. and 11. Chap. he handleth the matter of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination. For all the reſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon that: namely, who ſhould receiue the worde, and who ſhould not, who ſhould belieue, &amp; who not, who ſhuld bee freed from ſin, who ſhould bee blinded, who ſhould bee damned, and who ſhould bee juſtified. Seing therefore that both the ſending out of the preachers of the Goſpell, and the word it ſelf be of God, it is certaine that it lyeth in Gods hand onely to juſtifie vs. And ſurely this ſtable ſentence and immoveable neceſſitie of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination,<note place="margin">Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt bee taught &amp; preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> is a moſt neceſſary doctrine to bee taught. For we are ſo weake that if it were in our handes, very few or rather
<pb facs="tcp:5429:34"/> none ſhould bee ſaved. For the Devill wold overcome vs. Yet now ſeeing this ſentence &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God is moſt ſure &amp; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, ſo that it cannot be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged or altered by any creature, we haue then good hope to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome at the length theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of ſinne, although that now they rage in our fleſh.</p>
            <p>But theſe curious men (who before they haue learned Chriſt &amp; the vertue of his Croſſe,<note place="margin">A Caveat for curious Chriſtians.</note> doe ſearch the profunditie &amp; depth of predeſtination, labouring in vaine to inquire whether they are predeſtinat to life or death) muſt bee rayned, ſtrained and kept back with ſome holy bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle. For without all doubt, theſe men by this their fooliſh curioſitie, will leade &amp; learne to caſt themſelves headlong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:5429:35"/> the confuſion of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or into the bottomles pit of deſperation. But thou (deare Chriſtian) ſee that in reading &amp; learning holy things thou follow the order and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode ſet downe heere in this place by the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Learne this godly Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode.</note>Firſt of all learne the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt, that thou maiſt acknowledg that al thy ſtrength and power availeth to nothing, but to ſinning. Furthermore, that by faith thou mayſt daily wraſtle with thy fleſh, as hee hath taught thee in the 7. firſt Chapters. Finally, after that thou bee come to the 8. Chap. that is, after that thou haſt tryd the croſſe and tribulation, after thou haſt had experience of this wholſome mortification, often to bee repeated, then firſt of all
<pb facs="tcp:5429:35"/> will this neceſſitie of predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, waxe ſweet vnto them, then thou ſhall firſt feele in the 9. 10. and 11. Chapters, how full of comfort and conſolation this doctrine of predeſtination is. For vnleſſe thou haſt had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and tryall of tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:<note place="margin">Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion onelie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable to thoſe which are well exerci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</note> vnleſſe thou haſt felt thy ſelf to haue beene brought ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme even vnto the gates of hell (as wee ſee in David and other Saints) thou canſt not beare or brooke this doctrine and ſentence of predeſtination without perill and danger, with a certaine murmuring &amp; grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of nature againſt GOD. Therefore it is needfull and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie that olde Adam ſhould firſt be mortified, that the ſenſe of the fleſh ſhould bee beaten down, that the ſucklings ſhould firſt grow vp in Chriſt before
<pb facs="tcp:5429:36"/> they drinke of this ſweete Cup of wine. For even heere alſo there is in every one a certaine infancy &amp; childhood, who hath in the meane time neede to bee fed with milke, vntill hee bee acuſtomed to eat ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger meats.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 12</note>In the twelfth chapter hee doeth annex and adjoyne cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine admonitions and precepts For this order the Apoſtle is wont to obſerue in all his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles,<note place="margin">The ſecond part of this Epiſtle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſtian converſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> that firſt hee doth teach Chriſt and Faith: afterwardes he doth exhort to good works, and a continuall mortification of the fleſh. Wherefore he doth teach heere good workes in deed, and the true worſhip of God. And heere he maketh all Chriſtians to bee Prieſts, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding them to offer not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, either Oxen or Gotes (as it was the cuſtome of the Law)
<pb facs="tcp:5429:36"/> but to offer themſelues a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſacrifice,<note place="margin">A ſpirituall prieſthood.</note> mortifying the old Adam. Furthermore hee doth delyver out moſt briefly vnto vs the inſtitution and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Chriſtian maners: as how we ſhold teach, preach, rule, and govern namely, in the Church: how we ſhould ſerue our neighbour, how we ſhould ſuffer tribulations: to be briefe, how it behoveth a Chriſtian to behaue himſelfe towardes his friends and enemies. And theſe are truely good workes of a Chriſtian man, which do flow out of Faith, as from a fountaine and head ſpring: Yea which doe even make a violent erup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For faith (as I haue ſaid) is not ydle:<note place="margin">Papiſtes works wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they are.</note> But the workes of the Iuſticiaries which are done without this liuely flame of Faith in the heart, are but hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites
<pb facs="tcp:5429:37"/> purple ſhow, and fained colours, wherewith they paint themſelues outwardly, which as inwardly they are full of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, avarice, filthines, &amp; deceit.</p>
            <p>In the 13. chapter hee teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs to bee obedient to earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and worldly Magiſtrates,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 13 Obedience to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</note> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all power is of GOD. For thogh the adminiſtration of the ſword, and theſe politicall and civill Lawes doe helpe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the juſtification of the heart: notwithſtanding becauſe that power and authoritie is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and appoynted of God, to the maintenance and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the peace of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, that malefactors might bee puniſhed, and good men defended: therefore it is to be reverenced and honoured even of the Saints of God and righteous men, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſtand not in neede of that
<pb facs="tcp:5429:37"/> authoritie. At the laſt he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth ſummarily al duties in this one worde Loue.<note place="margin">Loue is a ſhort ſum of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> And whereas he propoſed Chriſt as the cauſe &amp; author of our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, now heere after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſort hee proponeth and ſetteth him forth as an example: namely that wee imitating and following Chriſt, ſhould ſo ſerue our neighbour, as Chriſt hath ſerved vs.</p>
            <p>In the 14.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 14</note> Chap. hee teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the weake in faith not as yet expert and cunning in Chriſtian libertie,<note place="margin">Patience.</note> ought to bee patiently tolerated and borne withall through loue: alſo how wee ought to vſe that libertie not to any offence, but to the inſtruction and edifying of the weake conſcience of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. For vnleſſe the offending of the weake bee diligently and
<pb facs="tcp:5429:38"/> warely avoyded, there will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a diſcord and contempt of the Goſpell: whoſe dignitie and renoune it ſtands vs greatly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon to conſerue and keepe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violate. Wherefore it were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to yeeld for a tyme to the weake in faith, vntill they bee confirmed, than that the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell ſhould bee contemned or ſuppreſſed. And this is the chef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt worke of Chriſtian loue and Charitie, which verie many in theſe our dayes haue neede of, who abuſe their libertie by ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of fleſh, &amp; by other means, hurting weake conſciences, yea making them to ſtumble as it were in the entry and doore of Chriſtianity, before they know the liberty of Chriſt, and the way of righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 15</note>In the 15. Chap. yet once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine hee propoſeth Chriſt to
<pb facs="tcp:5429:38"/> bee followed, that by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample wee ſhould ſupport and beare with the weake whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they bee, whether ſinners,<note place="margin">Weak bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren oght to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</note> vnlearned, rude, and vnskilfull, or thoſe which otherwiſe are evill mannered, or of naughty conditions. For even thoſe are not ſtreight way to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, but rather to bee tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and ſuffered vntill they be better amended. So our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt (as wee ſee in the Goſpell) did beare with our ſins and offences: yea and at this day doth tolerate our ſinnes, errors, and imperfections, ever reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his right hand to helpe vs, ever ayding vs through his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable mercie.</p>
            <p>Moreover hee prayeth for the increaſe of their faith, peace, and joy of conſcience, alſo prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them, and committing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:5429:39"/> to GOD: yet once againe hee commendeth alſo and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his office, namely how hee may glory in that hee handleth and medleth with Gods buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and matters, how that he doth and hath preached throgh the grace which hee hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of God, being alſo called from heaven by God, and not by any man. By and by after, (ſetting before them the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Macedonians in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſted of a little <hi>Exordium</hi> or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuation) hee doth verie civil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take an occaſion to beg and craue almes of them for the poore Saintes in Hieruſalem.<note place="margin">Almes to be given to the poore Saints.</note> To bee briefe, whatſoever this moſt Apoſtolicall breaſt doeth, or ſpeaketh it is meere Charity and loue, meere works of ſaith and of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Thus thou haſt (gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)
<pb facs="tcp:5429:39"/> heere in this Epiſtle moſt fully &amp; abſolutely ſet out what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever appertaineth any way either to Chriſtian life,<note place="margin">The Epiſtle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine for a Chriſtian man.</note> or iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication: what Chriſtians ought chiefly to learne, namely what the law is, what the Goſpell is, what ſinne, grace, faith, juſtice or righteouſneſſe, Chriſt, God good workes, charitie, loue &amp; hope is: briefly in what thing the ſumme of all Chriſtianitie doth conſiſt: how a Chriſtian ought to behaue himſelfe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his neighbour, whether they bee good or bad, weake, or ſtrong, friends or foes. Laſt of all how wee ſhould behaue our ſelves towards our ſelues, the Apoſtle doth ſo diligently fortifie and ſtrengthen all theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hings by Scripture, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irme them by his own example <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the example of the Prophets,
<pb facs="tcp:5429:40"/> that thou canſt not heere deſire or wiſh any thing more, or more plaine and manifeſt. For (no doubt) it was the Apoſtles minde to comprehend in this Epiſtle ſummarily, &amp; to handle compendiouſly the whole Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and whatſoever belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to Chriſtian learning and inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, alſo to prepare a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode and briefe introduction, vnto all the writings of the old Teſtament, namely, Moſes and the Prophets. For whoſoever hath red this Epiſtle well, and throughly digeſted it in his minde,<note place="margin">A profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</note> that man hath a moſte ſure and certaine methode to all the old Teſtament. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as I admoniſhed before, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heere nowe I doe exhort you that you would (as Moſes doth in the 11 chap. of Deut.) lay vp theſe things in your hearts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> childre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5429:40"/> to the end that by a continuall recording &amp; repeating of them they may be made by all means moſt familiar vnto you.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt chap. containeth ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutations or commendations: to which hee adjoyneth a verye good and moſt neceſſary admo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nition, namely that we ſhould ſhunne &amp; eſchue (as the plague and extreame infection &amp; poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of faith) the doctrines and traditions of men where-with the Goſpell and worde of God being contemned) the falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles do ſeduce &amp; withdraw from Chriſt the hearts of the ſimple.<note place="margin">Traditions not to bee received.</note> For the Apoſt. foreſaw in the Spirit, that there ſhould ariſe and ſpring certaine Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſtes (for they are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie the name of Romans) out of Rome, and Romans: who by their wicked and blaſphemous, moſt diviliſh and ſathanical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretals,
<pb facs="tcp:5429:41"/> and their whole den of mans lawes and traditions, as by a moſt waſt floude and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uge, wold labor to drowne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tinguiſh, and deſtroy not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> this excellent Epiſtle, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the whole body of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at the doctrine of fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Spirit: inſomuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they ſhould leaue vs nothing but this Idoll our belly,<note place="margin">Papiſts bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gods.</note> whoſe worſhippers he doth call them heere,<note place="margin">Philip 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and moſt plainely in the Epiſtle to the Philippians. For (ſaith he) there be many walke of whom I haue told you often, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd now tell you weeping, they are the enemies of the Croſſe of Chriſt whoſe God is their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and their glory, to their ſhame, they are world<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded. The GOD of all Pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> bruſe and beate downe Sathan and his kingdome vnder our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5429:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
